Well, it sure was nice to meet all the
indigenous peoples of the Americas in
the last video. But hold on to your
butts because here come the Europeans,
y'all. And if you're in the mood to
understand the causes of European
exploration, then I'm in the mood to
explain it up real nice for you. So, if
you're ready to get them brain cows
milt, let's get to it. Okay, the first
thing you need to know is that Europeans
didn't just wake up one day and go
exploring for poops and giggles. It was
actually the result of a bunch of
interweaving developments that occurred
in the century prior to this period.
Now, if you'll recall from your world
history class from about 1200 to 1450,
Europe was kind of a laughable side note
on the stage of world powers. You know,
while China and the Islamic empires and
all the rest were positively dominating
everybody's crap across Afroureasia,
European states were decentralized and
kind of pitly. Oh, and by the way, if
you want note guys to follow along with
this video and all my videos along with
quizzes to help you remember this stuff,
well, check that link in the
description. Anyway, Europe's population
tanked on account of the black plague
and they experienced hard times
agriculturally during a period of global
cooling known as the little icing. But
in the century before our period starts
in this course, Europeans were about to
find some power pants and put them all
the way on. And let me tell you about
the developments that helped them do
this. First, the climate got warmer and
then that led to second improved
productivity in agriculture aided by new
farming techniques and technology.
Third, more food led to more babies and
European population started growing
quick, fast, and in a hurry. Fourth,
that situation led to a revived desire
to trade on the world market, especially
for those tasty luxury goods from Asia.
And then fifth, the Renaissance began in
Italy and then spread throughout Europe
and that constituted a kind of cultural
rebirth in various European states. And
six, that cultural rebirth went
handinhand with various movements of
political unification which strengthened
the governments of several European
states. So all of this taken together
meant that Europe became far more stable
and powerful than it had been in a long
time and they were ready to go out
exploring. Okay, so those are the
reasons that Europeans could explore.
But now the question dear pupil is why
did they explore? And I got three
reasons for you. Gold, god and glory. So
the first motive for European
exploration is gold which is a funner
way of saying that they went exploring
on account of economic motives. Now as I
mentioned before some Europeans were
getting wealthier and they wanted more
and more of those luxury goods from
Asia. But as it turned out they had a
big fat problem on their hands. You see
at this point in history the main trade
routes connecting Europe to Asia were
land routes. The most notable of which
for our purposes was the Silk Road. But
in 1453, the Ottoman Empire went ahead
and conquered Constantinople, which was
a key choke point for European trade
with Asia. And since those rascally
Ottomans now dictated the terms of
trade, Europeans wanted to figure out
another way to the Asian market. And so
they looked at the ocean and were like,
"Hey, you know how we got a bunch of
boats?"
>> Now, I know this might sound crazy, but
I bet we could float to Asia. You're a
dang genius. And so combine the rising
European demand for Eastern goods with
improved banking systems that help
facilitate trade, and baby, you got an
exploration stew going. So the first
mover in that regard was Portugal. And
under the leadership of our boy Prince
Henry the Navigator, the Portuguese
sailed around Africa in order to access
the riches of the Indian Ocean trade.
And then in 1498, Vasco Dama was the
first to successfully sail around the
Cape of Good Hope and establish a
Portuguese presence in the east. And
Portugal's method here was to establish
trading posts all around the African
coast and throughout the Indian Ocean.
So that means that the Portuguese didn't
really establish what we'd think of as
colonies in all these places, but
instead they created what's known as a
trading post empire. And by the end of
the 16th century, the Portuguese had
come to dominate the Indian Ocean trade,
which made them fabulously wealthy. And
right about then, Portugal's neighbor
Spain, or if you're sassy, Espa, decided
that they too wanted to cash in on the
riches of maritime exploration. But
since the Portuguese went ahead and
lifted their leg and peed all over the
Indian Ocean trade, thereby claiming it
as a dog might claim a mailbox. The
Spanish wanted to find a different way
to the Asian markets. And wouldn't you
know it, right about then, a Genoise
sailor by the name of Christopher
Columbus showed up in the Spanish court
asking the monarchs to fund an
exploration westward across the Atlantic
Ocean. This happened to be right after
the Portuguese told him no. So, you
know, big mistake. Anyway, after hearing
Columbus' request, King Ferdinand and
Queen Isabella were like, "Ain't no
idea. Here, take all our money." Now,
here's where I'd tell you that Columbus
wasn't the only one who believed that
the Earth was a sphere. Like, the
ancient Greeks mathematally
understood. Anyway, Columbus set sail
from Spain in 1492 in order to reach
Asian and Southeast Asian markets. But
even though everyone knew that the Earth
was a sphere, Columbus and all the
Matthew Matthew people underestimated
the size of the Earth by about 25%. And
so when he landed in the Caribbean,
Columbus was convinced that he had made
it all the way to Asia. Now, in time,
the Spanish would figure out exactly how
to squeeze enormous amounts of wealth
out of the new world. And that would
only further motivate them to continue
exploring these previously unknown
continents. But we're going to save the
rest of that juicy tale for the next
video. But for now, let's consider the
second cause of European exploration,
namely God. Which is to say they had
religious motives. Now, in order to
understand this, you're going to need to
know that Europe was going through a
period of religious crisis in the 15th
and 16th centuries. And while there were
religious minorities in Europe, most
notably Jews and Muslims, the dominant
belief system there was Christianity.
But it wasn't just any flavor of
Christianity. No, this was Roman
Catholic Christianity. And the Roman
Catholic Church had played a significant
role in creating a common culture
throughout Europe. But in the 15th
century, a few reformed-minded Catholics
started getting a little cranky about
what they saw as abuses and corruption
in the church. For example, they
criticized the church for the practice
of simony, which was the buying and
selling of important church positions.
That means it wasn't the most spiritual
people who were becoming priests or
cardinals or whatever. It was the people
who had enough money to buy their way
into the cloth. And that situation, not
surprisingly, resulted in quite a few
ecclesiastical turds whom the common
people found prodigiously stank. And
then the church also engaged in the sale
of indulgences which meant that people
could pay to have their sins or you know
their family sins forgiven and thus
secure an easier way to heaven. Now to
put it mildly the church officials loved
this because you know all them basilas
and golden toilets ain't going to pay
for themselves. Not even to mention that
this situation helped the elite maintain
positions of power. But in 1517 one of
those cranky reformers by the name of
Martin Luther stood up and called a turd
a turd. Now, he wrote a series of
complaints about the corrupted elements
of the church in a document known as the
95 thesis, then nailed it to the church
door in Vittenberg. Long story short,
that act launched the Protestant
Reformation and led to a permanent split
in the Christian church. And now what
you see is European states embracing
either Catholic Christianity or
Protestant Christianity. Furthermore,
since there was really no such thing at
this time as the separation of church
and state, the religious feud also
became a political feud with each
European power contending over who were
the true Christians and the most
powerful state. And predictably that led
to a series of religious wars in which
Europeans were killing other Europeans
to prove which one loved Jesus the most.
Anyway, all this is happening right at
the same moment when European states are
beginning to venture out into maritime
exploration. And they use that
opportunity to prove that their version
of Christianity was the best by
spreading it all over the dang world.
Take Spain for example. Since about the
8th century, Muslims have controlled
dang near all of the Iberian Peninsula.
But by the 13th century, they controlled
a much smaller portion of Spain known as
the Emirate of Granada. And that
happened because the Spanish gradually
had taken territory from them over time.
However, in 1469, a momentous event
occurred when the two most powerful
kingdoms in Spain were united by the
marriage of Isabella of Castile and
Ferdinand II of Aragon. And now that
their armies were combined, they had
more than enough power to lead the
Reconista, which finally ousted the
Muslims from Catholic Spain in 1492. And
then they further wielded their Catholic
hammer by instigating the Inquisition,
which eliminated religious descent in
Spain and expelled something like
200,000 Jews in the process. So, all of
that is going on at the very same moment
that Columbus, that saucy Italian
sailor, showed up asking for money to
find a westward passage to Asia. And
since the Spanish crown was positively
drunk on their success in killing and
torturing a bunch of denters in order to
prove the supremacy of Catholic Jesus,
they were more than willing to fund
Columbus' trip. I mean, for sure, they
wanted the wealth that came from such
trade, but they also reckoned that there
were probably a lot of people in Asia
who didn't believe that Catholic Jesus
was the best, and the Spanish had some
ideas about how to convince And since
the Protestant Reformation put a sizable
smackdown on the reign of Catholicism,
success in these missionary endeavors
gave them a chance to reassert Catholic
dominance. And finally, European states
were motivated to explore for the glory,
which is to say they had political
motive. Now, once contact was made
between the old and new worlds, it
quickly became a competition between
European states to acquire colonial
possessions in order to shift the
balance of power toward themselves. And
throughout the 16th century, Spain was
for sure winning this game because they
colonized the crap out of the Americas.
And so other European powers, not too
stoked about Spain possessing the one
ring to rule them all, decided that they
too needed to explore and colonize, if
only to keep the balance of power
straight. Additionally, political change
was occurring in some European states in
which large multithnic empires were
breaking apart while small kingdoms were
uniting and becoming more powerful, like
we saw for example with Isabella and
Ferdinand in Spain. Anyway, this new
political reality coming into being was
called the nation state, which by
definition is a political entity that
governs more or less a single unified
people. And again, as nation states
begin to emerge, it promotes fierce
competition to become the most powerful.
And don't forget that the Protestant
Reformation added a religious ingredient
to this competition. And you know, I
mean, if you know anything about
anything, religious competition
typically does not chill people out. So,
you know, it got nasty. So, a good
example of that competition was the spat
between Spain and Portugal regarding
their colonial claims in the Americas.
And that kind of competition is
certainly going to lead to armed
conflicts later, but this is an example
of the conflict being solved
diplomatically, which is to say, they
used their talkie-talkie parts and then
hugged it out in a tree. So the short
version is that both states were getting
angry because their colonial possessions
in the Americas were starting to
overlap. And so because they were both
Catholic states, the pope settled this
dispute by drawing a line of demarcation
which settled the question of which new
world territories belong to whom. Now in
1494 that line was moved slightly and
then codified in the treaty of Torisas
which established Portugal's claim to
part of Brazil and then Spain's claim to
pretty much every other part of
Americas, much of which they didn't even
know was there yet. Now clearly the pope
did not find it necessary to invite the
indigenous peoples of the Americas into
that negotiation. But as we're going to
see in the next few videos, they were in
no way stoked about this arrangement.
All right. Well, you can click here to
keep reviewing my other unit one videos,
and you can click here to grab my video
note guides, which are going to help you
get all the content of this course
firmly crammed into your brain folds.
And I'll catch you on the flip-flop. I'm
La.